Software engineering radio episode 14,
interview with Ted Neward.
Ted, welcome to uh Software Engineering
Radio. Um today we want to talk about uh
.NET and uh C# 3.0 and in general .NET
language evolution.
Um but before we start, I guess you
would like to uh introduce yourself a
little bit so that the listeners know
who they're listening to.
Well, um
my name is Ted Neward and um as we say
here in the States, I'm a big geek.
Um
I play with uh you both Java and .NET
platforms. And
I've got a couple of books out. Um
Effective Enterprise Java came out uh um
I guess a year and a half ago now. Gosh,
how time flies.
And uh I did I co-authored C# in a
Nutshell and SSIS Essentials, which is
also known as the Roter book.
Mhm.
And I've got uh a couple more that I'm
working on now that when we get closer
to publication, I'll probably make some
uh some sort of formal announcement
about that. They're a couple of .NET
related books.
I just keep bouncing back and forth
between the two platforms. It's kind of
fun.
Yeah, that's interesting. Not not not
too many people do that actually. So
you're probably in a good position to
compare the two platforms. So So can you
say something, you know, I mean, not
that X is better than Y, but maybe I
prefer to use X for task such and such
or and I use .NET for this and that. So
do you have any preferences there?
Well, you know,
in a lot of respects, the two really are
kind of
the phrase I like to use when I'm when
I'm asked this question at conferences,
the phrase I like to use is that they
they are really evil twin brothers. You
know, I mean, if you look at all the the
the the myths and fairy tales and so
forth, whenever you have, you know, twin
brothers, you know, each one believes
the other one is evil and each you know,
they're basically fighting over who gets
to inherit the kingdom when the king
dies. And in this case, of course, the
king is Cobol.
Mhm.
And
um
they really are
you know, in many respects,
um they really are twin brothers. You
know, they're they're genetically
almost identical. They really have a lot
of the the the same basic um same basic
parts. They're they're made very very
similar to one another. And as a result,
you can really use
either one to accomplish any particular
task.
What's really different about them is
sort of the culture that surrounds them.
You know, in some cases, the culture
that birthed them, but more often than
not, the culture that surrounds them.
You know, so for example, I mean, this
shouldn't come as a great surprise to
anybody. If I want to build something
that's very specific to the Windows
platform, .NET tends to be the better
platform to do it with. If I want to
build something that runs
cross-platform, Java turns out to be the
better platform to use. And that that
should not surprise anybody.
Um but there had there there's some
interesting sort of
uh subtitles that go along with that,
which say, you know, .NET held as a
important value that you be able to
reach into the underlying platform and
access things that are below
the managed environment. You know, like
so .NET has a very very good
platform interop story, platform
invocation story. Java, on the other
hand, tries very hard to hide the
underlying platform. And so, Java
suggests that everything you want to do
should be in Java. And as a result, you
get into situations like the distinction
between Swing
where Java tries to do all of the
painting and all of the event handling
logic for you,
and WinForms, which says, "No, we want
to basically shell out to, you know, Win
user32 and GDI
and let the operating system handle all
that stuff." Which is kind of what IBM
has been able to do with SWT.
Yeah.
You know, so you get you get some really
interesting sort of technological you
know, discussions there.
The one thing that I do see, you know,
that is a very common distinction, and I
won't say that that I necessarily prefer
one platform over the other the other
for any one thing.
But one area that you do see is, you
know, Java has a tendency to drive a lot
of the the back-end enterprise traffic.
A lot of J2EE going out there in the
world. And .NET has a tendency to do a
lot of the front-end um user interface
type stuff. And so, as a result, you get
a lot of people who are saying, "Let's
do a WinForms front-end talking to a
J2EE back-end." And in a lot of
respects, that really works out really
really well cuz you're sort of
leveraging each platform for what its,
you know, cultural strengths turns out
to be.
One thing that I that I've heard a
couple of times is that specifically in
the in the embedded world, like not not
deep embedded, but this portable PDA
thing phone thing that the compact
framework seems to be a bit more
feature-rich than J2ME, so that that
that's something that I heard before.
Yeah, see I don't know much about the
compact space, so I couldn't really I
couldn't really say a lot, you know, to
either side. I do know that
um you know, for a long time, it really
seemed like neither one was doing a
great job of
capturing that market. And it may be,
you know, now that
uh you know, Pocket PC is running on the
uh the Treo,
you know, that may signal a significant
shift in the balance of power between
the two. But I, you know, I've known a
couple of people who have tried to reach
or I tried to write
um
you know, what let's let's call them
portable device programs who really
didn't like either platform. You know,
they did they I don't know anybody who's
used both, but I've talked with people
who do Compact Framework who've said,
"Oh, I really don't like Compact
Framework. It's such a pain in the ass."
And I know people who've used J2ME and
said exactly the same thing.
Yeah.
So, you know, I don't know if that's
just grass is greener on the other side
or if that's, you know,
actual, you know,
we the both of these platforms need a
lot of work yet. I I don't know. I don't
know.
So, after looking at the two platforms,
let's maybe,
before we go into details about C#,
compare the two languages a little bit.
One thing that I kind of always think is
that C# has a faster pace with regards
to language evolution. There are more
interesting new features. So, what do
you think about the current state, like
if you compare C# to, with I don't know,
Java 5? Um
any opinion on that?
Well,
you know, it's interesting because
on the one hand, you know, you have
Microsoft who owns this the the C#
space, right? I mean, Microsoft has done
a very a very good job of putting C# the
language definition into the public
domain. It is a, you know, it is an
established standard that is owned
through ECMA and ISO.
Oh, yeah.
Um you know, but on the other hand,
clearly the C# language is being defined
by Anders Hejlsberg. And so, if Anders
decides that he wants a new feature in
the C# language, you know, it will
happen. There's really no question about
that. Um and in some respects, the
standardization efforts are almost an
afterthought. You know, you really don't
see like what you see in the Java space
where you have sort of a community-based
effort around defining the language. But
at the same time,
you know, the community-based approach
is not always the greatest one as well
because what you end up with sometimes
is,
you know, too many cooks running around
inside this space
um trying to to define, trying to
change, trying to modify, etc. the
language. I know I've been a part of
several Java Community Process Expert
Groups, including one, the Annotations
Facility that was part of Java 5.
Mhm.
And in some cases, you know, what you
get is just good old-fashioned committee
um schizophrenia. You know, you've got
15 people on a committee, and so you
have 15 slightly different ideas or in
some cases radically different ideas as
to what exactly you should do. And that
that that becomes, I think, something of
an impediment to progress.
But at the same time, you know, this is
where you get into some of the cultural
differences. If Sun were to turn around
and say, "We're just going to define
what the next version of Java would be
like, and the rest of you, you don't
like it, you can just go take your ball
and play someplace else."
Yeah.
The Java community will crucify them.
Microsoft does that, and the Microsoft
community says, "Okay, cool. Microsoft
is is innovating. Microsoft is going off
and doing new things."
So, there's this culture in the Java
space that I think inherited from, you
know, the same culture in in the Unix
space.
Mhm.
Says, "Hey, you know, no one vendor
should control this process." And as a
result, innovation has tended to be a
little bit slower.
That said, Java 5 was the most
innovative language changes to the Java
platform since forever, since JDK 1.1,
quite frankly.
So, I think Sun is not afraid in some
cases to go off and do things to the
language. They They have a tremendous
concern over backwards compatibility.
You know, because the platform is 10
years old at this point. You know, that
that You You go back and look at the
changes between C++ between, you know,
1989 and 1999.
You know, there's There's There's a
point at which you say, "I really can't
radically innovate anymore."
Yes.
And Microsoft is approaching that point,
too. You know, they're getting to a
point where they're going to have to
slow down a little bit on some of the
radical innovation. Otherwise, they're
going to piss off a lot of the early
.NET programmers
who are going to say, "This isn't quite
what I had in mind when I signed up for
this gig."
But, you know, for the moment, Microsoft
is a little bit more of a free rein than
Sun does, and it looks like Microsoft is
willing to explore that and play with
that, and, you know, take it to the nth
degree, which Sun can't or won't, and
and I'll leave that at that.
Okay, then, let's look at those some of
those new features that are upcoming in
in .NET or C# 3.0. Actually, I heard
about some of the language features
we're going to talk about in a moment.
Are they actually C# specific, or are
they applicable for all those other .NET
languages like VB.NET, also?
In the case of talking about C#
3.0/LINQ,
they are all of them language. They They
I I When I When When LINQ first came
out, um I wrote a blog entry sort of
explaining all of the features and and
showing how they
what what what sort of IL they turned
into.
And so, the thing that that I called it
at the time, which a couple of people
sort of took me to task for, but I stand
by, is that all of the features in C#
3.0 are basically syntactic sugar.
Mhm.
Thing
it all they're really doing
is they are just saving you as the
author of the class or the author of the
code. They're just saving you from
having to type a little bit more.
And in some cases they're saving you
from typing a lot.
Yeah.
But there's no structural changes to the
CLR that that they had to do for for
project link.
Um and as a result the the the features
look a little bit different between C#
3.0 and VB 9.
Mhm.
So these are these are all compiler
tricks basically.
Okay. Since you already mentioned link,
which is actually spelled l i n q in
case people don't know, um why don't you
explain what what this is all about?
Well, link is it stands for language
integrated query and effectively it's
it's an attempt by Microsoft by by folks
within the Microsoft C# uh compiler
community
to say, "Look, you know, we do a
tremendous amount of work with data. You
know, whether it's relational data or
hierarchical data ala XML,
we do a tremendous amount of work with
data. So, what they want to do is they
want to make C# as a language friendlier
to working with data.
So,
what you know, at the surface level what
it looks like is they've embedded SQL
into language. Well, that's not exactly
true. What they've done is they've
embedded a number of features at the
language level
that they then make use of in order to
make it easier to insert, extract, and
examine relational data and hierarchical
data.
Most of the features, you know, that
we're going to talk about in terms of C#
3, most of them support the relational
data angle. The hierarchical data angle
turns out not to be too difficult to do
using the existing facilities of the
language.
Um most of what we're going to be
talking about will be to support the
relational aspects.
But regardless, the point of link is to
say you work with data. If you are a
practicing C# programmer, you work with
data. And right now, taking
library-based approaches like ADO.NET or
XML reader
is just awkward. There's no compile-time
safety. You're bridging across type
systems. There's
uh you know, there's a tremendous amount
of code that you, the programmer, have
to write in order to be able to work
with this, even if you use some of the
baked-in facilities like data set.
It's just too much work. And we should
be able to support this not just against
external relational data, but we should
be able to, for example, if I've got a
you know, if I've got a collection of
objects, excuse me, collection of
objects in memory,
Mhm.
it should be able to issue a
relational-like query using all the, you
know, predicate calculus and so forth
against that collection to make it easy
to find elements within that collection.
There should be no
um linguistic difference between
querying a collection and querying a
database, querying a table.
So so if we compare
uh link with things like, for example,
Hibernate, where you specify the query
inside a string and then pass it down to
the database, or even SQLJ, where you
have a bit of SQL embedded in the
language using a preprocessor,
how how how does link compare? Can you
Can you give our listeners a flavor of
how this will feel, taste, look like?
Well,
link is going to be very different from
Hibernate in the sense that
at its basic levels, link is not really
an object-relational mapping layer.
Um some of the guys who worked on link
uh like uh Luca I'm probably going to
mispronounce his name, but it's Luca
Bolognesi or something like that.
Mhm.
Um
you know, a lot of that work came out of
the work they did around the ORM stuff
that Microsoft was working on. Um object
spaces. So, a lot of those guys came
over to work on Link because it was sort
of related to, you know, what an ORM
does. But, at the end of the day, Link
is not really an ORM.
And there's an important distinction
there because an object relational
mapper says, "I will take the relational
data. I will take the rectangles, as
Eric Meier once put it. I will take
those and I will pound them into round
shape, you know, circles being the
common way that we represent objects
pictographically. We will pound them
into round shapes so that you can just
work with objects." And that's basically
what Hibernate does. Hibernate says,
"You just go ahead and walk up to the
Hibernate session and say that you want
to fetch a particular person object out
of the database, and I will go ahead and
create the SQL query for you, and I will
execute the query, and I will interpret
the results, and and shove it into a
person object and hand it back to you."
And there's a tremendous amount of
impedance mismatch that an ORM has to
overcome in order to maintain that
facade, in order to maintain that
objects first facade.
SQLJ tried to take sort of the opposite
approach. SQLJ said, "We are going to
create an embedded SQL
uh situation where we will take your SQL
statements that you you will write in a
Java, you know, what what they call the
SQLJ file.
We will extract your SQL statements,
and we will go ahead and translate that
code into making
the equivalent of ADO.NET in Java was
called JDBC. So, we'll go ahead and make
JDBC calls and we'll do, you know, we'll
generate all the X number of code
necessary to do that relational query,
extract that data, and pound it into,
you know, whatever in the in the case of
JDBC into a result set
that you want to try and extract it from
there.
The thing that Link does differently is
that it's not so much trying to say, "I
want to hide the relational database
from you behind a, you know, objects
first perspective," which is what
Hibernate and other ORMs do.
And it's not so much trying to
preprocess
as it is really, in many respects,
trying to integrate, hence the name,
um relational
syntax, relational theory as part of the
platform.
So, that again, one of the things you
can do with Link that you cannot do with
either Hibernate or with um with uh SQLJ
is you could do a relational query
across an in-memory collection.
Again, so if I have a a uh a list of T,
right? If I have a list of person
objects, I can issue a relational-like
query across that list of person types
to find all of the persons in that list
where first name equals Marcus.
Mhm. Right? And that's something that
Hibernate cannot do, that not easily at
least, unless you have some sort of JDBC
driver that knows how to do in-memory
query.
in-memory database, but that's a trick.
Yeah, well, and and, you know, there is
no such thing today that operates off of
a standard Java collection class.
Yeah.
Um and SQLJ, you know, again, you'd have
to have a JDBC driver. And again, that
only hand you know, that only handles
the situations where you have the
appropriate driver. It's not a sort of
universal solution, which, you know,
quite frankly,
this is this is very powerful, right?
The
um some of the features in Link are
designed to work off of the base types
that we work with every day in the
uh .NET base class library. So, for
example, anything that hands back an
IEnumerable,
right, can be used as part, you know,
you can do relational-like predicates
across. So, I can do, you know, selects
and groups and order bys and so forth.
Anything that that hands back an
IEnumerable, which is very, very
powerful.
Relational databases do quite a bit of
uh optimization if you pass them a an
SQL query. How is this handled in Link?
Is is the optimization still done in the
persistent store in case there is one
underlying the query, or does Link do
this somehow in memory, or or how do you
handle big data sets? Is there any kind
of lazy initialization or something?
Well, what Link does, and and when we
get into some of the features, you know,
it all of these features sort of stack
on top of one another to sort of explain
how Link will do this. But, Link does
not do
um what some people sort of looked at
when when they hear about this is they
sort of get this queasy feeling in their
stomach that says, "Oh my god, Link is
going to go off and pull the entire
contents of the table across the wire,
and then do the filtration on my side
inside the CLR." And that's not the
case.
And obviously, nobody would seriously
expect that Microsoft proposes such an
approach. So, there must be something
else. Question is just how.
Well, what they do is using um extension
methods in C# 3, the actual the actual
implementation of how the the query of
how the the filtration and so forth will
carry out is actually deferred against
what you're going up against. So, for
example, if you do this against a um If
this against the in-memory collection,
right, if you do this against a list of
T,
then
the the extension methods that support
in-memory query will kick in.
If, however, you do this against a
relational database, if you do this
against a database object that you have
opened, you know, you've opened a
connection against Northwind or whatnot,
then a different set of extension
methods kick in, and those extension
methods actually use
um expression trees. So, what they do is
they look at your your literally, they
look at your source. This is partly
what, you know, this is this is what the
C# compiler does for you.
Is it looks at your source, and it
builds an expression tree, and hands
that expression tree to the
database-driven extension method, who
then feeds that across the wire to SQL
Server,
who then does his usual crop of
optimizations against it to retrieve
that that stuff efficiently.
So, in essence, what they do is they do
the right thing, regardless of which
direction you go with this.
Yeah. Um but you do have symbolic
integration, right? So, you have a
variable of type, I don't know, string,
which has which holds a name, and then
you can natively write this query
passing in the string, and then you get
back an object of type, I don't know,
collection, which contains the result of
the query, right? So, and you can use
variables from the normal source code
inside the the queries, because it's the
same thing. They are normal source code.
That's correct. That's correct. What
It's It's It's interesting, you know,
because what they've what they've really
done is they've used a lot of the um the
language type system to our benefit,
right? So, that if I'm looking at, you
know, a a customer object or a person
object, I see the actual object type. If
And this is one of the areas that ORMs
have traditionally fallen down.
Right.
Um if it is a customer object, like the
full definition of the table, you know,
then the ORM is happy. If, however, all
I wanted to pull back was just the first
name and last name of the customer and
nothing else, the ORM has historically
said either A, I need to hand you a
generically typed thing, right? Like
JDBC hands back a result set, you know,
another ORM might hand back a hash map
or something equivalent.
Or you would have to explicitly define a
type, you would have to create your own
sort of customer light type
that would be retrieved in the event of
this query. And, you know, you would
have to go off and create that type and
create the mapping and the binding and
so forth to that particular type in
order to make all that stuff work, in
order for the ORM to appropriately map
between the columns of the database and
the type that you're creating.
This is actually where uh I don't know
how much you or your listeners are aware
of the hype going on surrounding Ruby
and Ruby on Rails.
I think they are.
Yeah, well, this is where a lot of the
the Rails hype is really building
because Rails has some meta object
facilities within it such that they can
do what, you know, the active record
pattern, where I'll just get back an
object where the fields correspond
directly to the columns.
Mhm.
And I don't have to worry about defining
that object up front. And that turns out
to be again a very, very powerful uh
system, but it's also very, very
simplistic. The object maps directly to
the table.
The thing that Link does is I can go
ahead and define these classes up front
if I choose. And there is a tool that
Link provides that will actually go to
the database and generate these types
for you, so you can use it, in a sense,
as a traditional ORM, sort of a
database-driven ORM. Or you can
handwrite these classes and define their
mappings using .NET attributes, as many
ORMs do, to define what you want those
things to look like when you pull them
out.
So, in a lot of respects, link, you
know, the thing that I like about it so
much is it doesn't go off and create
unique different rules that, you know,
that that you as the programmer have to,
you know, it's not a new set of rules,
it's not a different set of rules. It's
all the same basic facilities that you
as a programmer are already familiar
with in the C# space. But, they're able
to go off and do things with these rules
because of these additional syntactic
sugar elements that they've added
to make it much easier to go fetch that
stuff, to go work with that stuff, to
have statically verified type safety,
which a traditional ORM has not been
able to guarantee.
So,
two other features are uh implicitly
typed variables and anonymous types.
Now, if I got that right, what you just
said, then what you can do is you can
query against the database and you get
back a collection of objects and the
type of this object, of which the
collection is built, is actually
dynamically created and you don't have
to declare it. So, you can basically
write some object result equals and then
you get back something that implicitly
builds the type that results from the
fields you queried against. Is that
right?
Close, but not quite.
Okay. I tried.
and this is this is a a very common
misunderstanding with respect to link is
that it's not
it's not done dynamically at run time.
Okay.
all done by the compiler at compile
time.
Right.
So, when I when I write a query, right?
When I say select first name,
last name,  age from person, or
in in C# link, it's actually from DB
select uh first name comma last name
comma age.
They reverse the the from and the
select.
Yeah.
Um
the
basically what the compiler does is he
looks at that expression. He looks at
that that you know what you're what
you're fetching back and he compares it
against what he knows.
So if you're doing it against a database
type, if he has information, right? And
again, this is compile time. If he has
information as to what first name, last
name, and age are,
he can generate at that point what they
call anonymous type. He can build a type
that has no name. Just like in C# 2.0,
we have anonymous methods, right? Where
you can define the method without a
name.
He builds that at the time of
compilation so that we're not
constructing types dynamically on the
fly at run time.
Cuz you know, that that would still take
a great deal of time and would be a you
know, very very expensive. And truth be
told, we have all the information we
need at compile time to be able to
construct this type. So why would you
want to defer that until run time if you
know, 99% of the time
this type is going to be known at
compile time. Because you know that
first name is a string and last name is
a string and age is an int. So let's
just generate a little What we're really
doing is we're generating tuple types,
right? We're generating just
basically you know, bundles of data.
Structs.
Exactly. We're generating structs. And
part of what they'll do is in this
anonymous type definition, they will
generate these structs to be exactly
what you would write, you know, if you
were a quote unquote proper
object-oriented programmer. They will
have properties, they will have a
constructor,
they make it easy for you to do
construction of these anonymous types,
right? What they call object
initializers.
You know, and you're getting a fully
fledged object. It's even got a two
string and an equals method, you know,
which is nice.
Yeah.
Um
and that's important because we want to
be able to compare these things. We want
to be able to do equality comparisons on
these objects just as we would for any
other object. They're literally coding
up what we in the Java space refer to as
data transfer objects
Yep.
for you. And you don't have to write a
damn thing to do it. Which And And
again, it's all It's not It's not duck
typing in the traditional sense that you
think of duck typing like, you know,
Dave Thomas uses in Ruby. These are all
still statically typed. So, you still
have to obey the rules of the type
verifier and the type system and so
forth.
Okay.
But
Go ahead.
Yeah, and then that's why you said it's
all basically syntactic sugar because
people don't have to write the type of
the variable, they just write var if I
know correctly, and then the compiler
the compiler infers the type and kind of
assigns it automatically.
That's correct. That's exactly correct.
The The The compiler is the one who
generates this type. The compiler is the
one who defines the elements on this
type. And then once the compiler is done
it behaves exactly like a type, you
know, that you had written by hand.
Okay.
The other The other feature you
mentioned, the anonymous variables?
Yeah.
Uh or I'm sorry, the implicitly typed
variables.
Implicitly Yeah, right.
Again, all they're really doing is
they're saving you some typing so that
if you say var X equals  hello,
the compiler looks at that and says,
"Well, gosh, I can infer that that is a
string. So, I will go ahead and make X a
reference to type string."
Yep.
Right. I mean again, all you're really
doing is you're saving the programmer
from some typing at some at what at one
level. But then at a more important
level, what you're really saving the
programmer from knowing is the exact
type that that declaring a reference to,
which is important when we work with
anonymous types because in an anonymous
type you won't know the type. You
wouldn't be able to write the name even
if you wanted to.
Exactly. Right.
So, these two work hand in hand to allow
you to be able to say var x equals,
right? Or basically for each per ends
var x in the returned query results, now
x is a reference to that anonymous type
and I can say x.firstname,
x.lastname, x.age and it's fully type
checked, it's fully syntax checked, it's
it's all the goodness that you want out
of a statically typed programming
language. But, it saves the programmer
from having to know a lot of those
really extraneous details up front.
It's actually quite cool, isn't it? I
mean, it's really interesting to to have
this kind of combination between static
statically typed type systems and this
kind of It looks like dynamic typing. It
isn't, but it looks like a little bit
like it because you don't
Well, and that's one of the things I
think You know, Eric Meyer, who
who was involved in
an earlier research project called
C-Omega, um
which is still available on MS Research.
It runs on the .NET 1.1 platform. They
have not updated it for 2.0.
But, C-Omega was an attempt to do a lot
of these kinds of stuff. Eric is is
basically a researcher at heart. And so,
you know, you talk to him
and you know, you you're clearly
speaking with somebody who is grounded
in the academic community.
Mhm.
So, be prepared to, you know, have have
your your ears burn a little bit as he
talks about monads and and you know,
monadic comprehensions and all of those
kinds of stuff. But, you know, it it it
is amazing. You know, I think a lot of
times we in the practicing industry have
a tendency to look at the academics and
say, "Ah, come on, they're a drain on
society. What are they doing that's
really practical and useful?"
Yeah.
The fact of the matter is that a lot of
the work that that, you know, Eric did
with C omega, I think directly fed into
some of what's going on here, if nothing
else because people like myself, you
know, who sort of keep an eye on what's
going on what's going on in the research
community, looked at that and said,
"Holy crap, that's good stuff. We want
that. I want to see that in my
practicing languages."
Mhm.
And, you know, some of that is really
spilling over into the Java community as
well. It's unfortunate that Sun does not
have the same
the same degree of of language
friendliness as Microsoft does over the
CLR.
Before you mentioned uh extension
methods as one of the implementation
tricks for fall link, can you maybe
elaborate two or three sentences on that
one?
An extension method syntactically and
and by the way, if people want to see,
you know, sort of source code examples
and so forth, again, I'll point them to
my blog uh blogs b l o g s
tedneward.com.
Um
And I'll I'll put a link into the show
notes.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah. You'll see it.
It's it's fairly easy to to spot off the
blog. But, I go through the syntax and
then also what the generated IL looks
like. So,
um when you write an extension method,
you're basically creating a static
method off of a static class that takes
as its first parameter what is
effectively a this pointer.
Mhm.
The reason and then they actually use
that keyword, right? You say object this
and then you give it the name. So, we're
reusing the this keyword.
Mhm.
What this does is this tells the
compiler that whenever you bring in that
namespace, whenever you say using
utilities, if that's the namespace that
your extension method is declared in,
your extension class,
Mhm.
what this means now is that the all of
the extension methods off of all of the
classes in that namespace are accessible
to you regardless of the class that
you're on. So, that now when you go to,
you know, in this C# 3 preview, when
you, you know, when you create an
instance of list type T, right? And you
say, you know, persons.
Intellisense kicks in and all of the
sudden you see a huge number of methods
that are not part of the list of T
class.
Mhm. Mhm.
These are extension methods that were
brought in because you did using
system.data
or system I'm sorry, system.query, not
system.data. That's the namespace in
which all of the link stuff lives.
So, what effectively happens is
the compiler turns around, what looks to
you like, you know, persons.select
and you pass in some, you know, some
lambda expression.
What that compiler turns that into is
system.query.
I forget the name of the class. I think
it's
search or something along those lines.
dot select parens the list, comma, and
then your lambda expression.
Mhm.
So, effectively, just as you as a
programmer would write a static class
with a bunch of utility methods on it
and then call into that static class
passing in the object instance you want
to pass,
the compiler's doing that for you now.
The compiler is literally generating
that code for you, but it looks to you
like it is a
it is a it is an instance method in the
traditional fashion and it behaves like
an instance method because you get a
this pointer.
And you have polymorphism?
Yes, you do. You can actually have
multiple extension methods and and it
and it depends on the the this parameter
in the extension method, right?
Whichever is the best match will be
used.
So, it's basically a way to add
additional methods to existing classes
without having to touch that the the the
class definition.
Correct. In in in the in some of the
linguistic space, they refer to these as
open classes where you can actually add
more functionality to a class that's
already been defined.
Which is another feature that the Ruby
folks tend to hype about.
Exactly. And it is a powerful feature,
but it's also a dangerous one because
you don't necessarily There's no point
at which in Ruby the class gets closed.
So, there's there's some danger where,
you know, okay, anybody can start adding
methods to classes and more importantly
changing the definition of some of those
classes. And an extension method cannot
change the definition of an existing
instance method. It'll It is always a um
weaker preference to an existing method
of the same name. So, I can't change the
definition of the two string method, for
example, on object because it's already
there. But, I can add a version of two
string that takes a parameter right,
that I could then, you know, that it
gets implicitly added to every object in
the system, quote unquote.
Something that you also also mentioned,
uh I don't know, 2 minutes ago was
lambda expressions. Is are they also
inside the C# now?
Well, the lambda's If you're If you're a
If you're a closet Lisp programmer, and
you're used to lambda expressions, you
will be disappointed by what we've got
inside of C# uh C# 3,
but at the same time, if you've never
used lambda expressions before, you will
You will be tickled because,
realistically speaking, a lambda is just
an easier way to write an anonymous
method. It's a It's a It's a more terse
syntax. And as a matter of fact, you
know, personally
not being a closet Lisp programmer, uh
not even being an out of the closet Lisp
programmer, um
you know, I I do not I do not think in
the lambda expression syntax. There are
some people who do, and, you know, I
wish those people well in their
recovery. But, um you know, I do not.
And as a result, the lambda expression
syntax for me is somewhat awkward and
difficult to to understand.
Um but, you know, for programmers out
there who do not want to grok the lambda
expression syntax, it's just another way
for writing an anonymous method. As a
matter of fact, that's exactly what the
compiler turns it into.
The The cool thing is that you can then
use those higher order functions where
you basically then say you have um a
collection and you can say collect and
then you pass in such a lambda
expression or select or map or anything
which which again gives you a much
terser syntax compared to iterating over
all that stuff.
Well, and and the thing is you could use
the same thing with an anonymous
delegate, right? Or with an existing
delegate, right? Where I can say, you
know, new delegate type, you know, so
it'll be like, you know, new I don't
know what the the the type would be in
link, but it would be, you know, I can
just literally pass, you know, the
method name, right? And and and he's
happy with it. So, we can still do a lot
of the higher order function stuff. It's
just we're not doing it
you know, the the the lambda syntax
doesn't have to be used to do it.
So, what you're saying is that the
important feature is not the lambda
expression, but rather the fact that you
can have typed function pointers which
you can pass around and which you can
pass into such a higher order functions.
Right. And and that is something that
we've had from the beginning, quite
frankly. And that is one of those those
elements of C# that I have always
favored over Java simply because, you
know,
that that turns out to be very powerful.
The The use of delegates was an
important first step, right? Defining
the delegate type was an important first
step. Then in 2.0, they introduced the
anonymous delegate type. Now in 3.0, we
shorten the syntax down to make it a
lambda expression.
Mhm.
You know, and suddenly we can start
stringing these types these these things
together and using them in very powerful
ways, you know, to create this this
higher order functionality
uh functional capabilities that you know
object-oriented languages have never
really had. I mean we could always pass
function pointers around in C++, but the
syntax was terrible and the functions
had to be defined in the traditional
sense.
Yeah.
I mean we could hand around instances of
the reflection method class,
but again, you know, to try and take one
of those guys to use one of those guys,
you had to go through a tremendous
amount of work in the java.lang.reflect
space to be able to get the method.
The delegate was a very very powerful
thing that they introduced in C# and for
years I have ranted and raved about
trying to get something equivalent to it
in Java and they've just, you know,
nobody's been listening or nobody really
understood why this was important.
Although I heard today in some other
other podcast that they're thinking
about putting method references into
Dolphin, which is Java 7 or something.
So maybe they've listened.
Well, and and I certainly I certainly
hope they have. You know, they they
added a new byte code in Java invoke
dynamic
to support the dynamic invocation of
methods to be able to support some of
these more loosely typed loosely bound
languages on the platform and that's a
good that's a good step.
Right.
And I I hope that they are in fact, you
know, actively considering, you know,
that kind of innovation for the Java
platform because frankly Java needs it
if they are to, you know, keep up, you
know, keep up with the Joneses in terms
of what Microsoft is doing in .NET. At
the same time I hope that if they make
those kinds of those those kinds of
innovative changes
they do so based on sound philosophical
principles and not just let's make Java
into the next 4GL right because that
that has a tendency to collapse under
its own weight.
Yeah. It seems like the .NET platform
and also Microsoft in that respect is
much more open to language diversity on
the .NET platform compared to Sun and
the Java platform. What's your
impression there?
Reading your blog, I I come across
languages like F sharp or Scala. So so
it seems like there is a lot of language
innovation going on on the .NET
platform.
Well, Scala actually, interestingly
enough, Scala is a language that was
originally designed for the Java
platform. And Martin Odersky, who is one
of the guys who was involved with the GJ
effort, which was an early
implementation of generics for Java, on
which Java's actual generic
implementation was based.
Um he's responsible for you know what's
going on in in Scala. He's he's part of
the the group uh at the Swiss University
that's working on it. So so Scala is
arguably more for the JVM than it is for
the CLR.
And quite frankly, there's a tremendous
amount of diversity in terms of
languages for the Java platform. As a
matter of fact, if you Google for that
exact phrase, languages for Java VM, you
will run across a page that's maintained
by, I believe his name is Patrick
Volkerding, um that he just tracks all
of the different languages that can
compile or interpreted on the Java
virtual machine.
And you will run across a just a
fascinating list
of of languages and and and and and
efforts and you know, one of the early
efforts, dating back as far as 1997,
was an effort, a language called Pizza,
p i z z a,
that um
again, Martin Odersky and Gilad Bracha
and a couple of other guys who were then
tapped for GJ,
were a part of. And Pizza is actually a
very interesting
combination of parametric polymorphism,
what we refer to as generics
Yeah.
and some higher order functionality
higher order function functionality uh
similar to what you see with like lambda
expressions and so forth. And this was
as far back as JDK 1.1.
So, you know, certainly there has been
this sort of
um
grassroots efforts in the Java space to
define and and use languages on the Java
platform. The big difference, and this
is the thing that frustrates me a great
deal about Sun, the big difference is
that Microsoft has encouraged
this multi-linguistic perspective. They
they have gone off and made it easy. At
one point they even had a guy whose job
was to, you know, if you wanted to bring
a language to the .NET platform uh Brad
Merrill would come out to your company
or come out to your organization and
say, "Here are the resources. Tell us
what you're running into. How can we
make your experience a better one?"
Mhm.
And you know, he had not just official
blessing, but I mean he was paid to do
this. This was his job was to go out and
evangelize the CLR as a platform for
your favorite programming language.
And that I mean that creates a culture
of, you know, of not just
experimentation, but of you know,
gratification. People are like, "Wow, I
can actually go off and do this thing
and feel like I will be recognized,
rewarded, whatever."
And as a result, you know, in given its
relatively short lifetime thus far,
there are tremendous number of languages
for the .NET platform.
And it seems like every time somebody
comes out with a language for the .NET
platform, somebody turns around and
comes out with an equivalent or similar
language for the Java platform.
Yeah.
There's there's a tremendous amount of
innovation going on. I believe
personally that the next 5 years will
see a real renaissance in language
design.
And I think what we're going to see is
that, you know, the the real positive
effect of Ruby and Ruby on Rails will
not be necessarily to convince us all to
go off and use the Ruby platform,
but to look at the Ruby language and
say, "Why exactly are people so
productive with that platform?" And what
can we do to, you know, to take
advantage of it? What can we do to
leverage that for the existing platforms
that companies have put billions, if not
billions of dollars of investment into.
Yeah.
That, I think, will be the the the the
big win.
Yes, I I agree completely. So, so, um
to to conclude this topic on on on Ruby
and and functional languages and
higher-order and metaobject protocols,
um
after the discussion before and after
learning that most of that kind of magic
stuff is done by the compiler, then I
guess you don't have a real metaobject
protocol in C# 3.0. And you what you
also not have is probably something like
a method not found method, you know,
like a default method that's called in
case another method that you invoke
Right.
can't be found because you you can't do
that because you still do it statically.
You just don't have have to write the
type.
That is correct. That is something that
we do not have in the the C# 3 space, in
the CLR itself, again, because these are
statically typed languages.
Um you know, now again, let's be really
careful here. There is nothing that
prevents a particular language from
implementing that kind of functionality
on top of itself.
Right.
Right. So, if if
uh there are people who are working on a
Ruby.NET uh implementation.
Mhm.
Uh there are people who are working on a
JRuby implementation, right? Ruby for
the JVM. Cuz the JVM has the same basic
limitation.
Right.
Um and
for that particular language, right? As
you're interpreting the the uh the
calls, if you're doing it in an
interpretive style or whatnot. Certainly
you could you could basically, you know,
encode a loop if you will that I will
reflectively search for this method and
if it's not there, reflectively search
for a missing method method and call
that method, which is exactly what Ruby
does, which is how we get active record
and all that good stuff.
Yep.
We could do that, but it would be
limited to that particular language and
it would clearly not be CLS compliant.
It would mean that you have an
interpreter running on top of the CLR or
or the JVM and it would not be native
CLR or JVM by default.
No, it wouldn't have to be an
interpreter and this is where I'm going
to go next. There are actually a couple
of hybrid approaches we could take
whereby, for example, and this is where
I come back to Eric Meyer. One of the
phrases that he's using and he wrote a
paper about this not too long ago for
Oopsla, where he says, "Statically typed
where we can be dynamically typed where
we have to be."
Mhm.
Which is a very very intriguing idea and
it stems from the basic fact that Visual
Basic is the only programming language
in the world that can switch between
early bound and late bound with
basically three keywords, right? Option
explicit on or option explicit off,
option strict on or option strict off.
That is actually really really powerful.
It means I can flip between reflective
invocation of methods and early bound
invocation of methods
within the same program.
This is this is really fascinating
because now what it means is if I can
look at the object type and determine
that the method that I want to call is
there,
then I can just go ahead and encode an
early bound method call right there.
Mhm.
If I'm looking, however, at an object
and the method is not present, I could,
as a compiler, emit the necessary calls
to do a reflective lookup and if that
reflective lookup fails, turn around and
call a missing method method, which
either is an extension method, you know,
to use the C# 3
syntax, or calls into something, you
know, looks for a missing method on that
type itself, right? Something that you
could maybe have inheriting from your
language's base class that inherits from
object or whatever, right? However you
want it to be able to encode that
missing method, you could do that. So,
we have
we have some interesting places where we
could do stuff like this. And see, this
is why I think, you know, people keep
talking about statically typed and
dynamically typed languages as if there
is no continuum between them.
There are a lot of interesting compiler
tricks that we can play,
right? You know, just speaking
practically, that
we have just begun to sort of scratch
the surface of.
So, I think we could get
a Ruby-like missing method functionality
without giving up the statically typed
platform that we're used to. And that, I
mean, that gets me just, you know, all
giggly inside because that
I mean, that gives us, you know, you
could really build, you know, a a
Ruby-like functionality on top of the
JVM or on top of the CLR. So, you get
all that, you know, goodness in terms of
productivity without losing the goodness
in terms of static typing.
Yeah. So, you you could have instead of
a class object, you could have a class
weak object, and if you inherit from
that one, you could do all the
invocations, for example, dynamically.
That would be really cool.
It It would It would even It wouldn't
even have to be a base class driven
scenario. It could literally be based on
how the compiler generated the code. So,
you've got class object, right? You got
a, you know, object O equals return
value from some method, and you call
O.foobar  .
My compiler could go ahead and say, "All
right, the object type definition does
not have a method call for foobar. So,
here's where I make the transition to be
dynamically typed. I will go ahead and
embed the code to reflectively look for
the method called
uh fubar and attempt to invoke it. And
if that's not there, then reflectively
look for the method called missing
method. And if that's not there, all
right, throw a throw a runtime
exception.
Yeah, give up.
Okay, um do you want to say two or three
words about F Sharp?
Um you know, F Sharp is is one of an
emerging class of functional object
hybrid languages. You know, so
functional languages have the the
interesting property that they attempt
to not produce side effects.
Mhm.
Right? So, when you um when you make a a
F Sharp
um when you make a method call, quote
unquote, when you when you call a
function, the idea is that there will be
no there there's no mutable state.
There's no changes. It's it's functional
in the mathematical sense rather than
the sense that we think about from a
procedural perspective.
Yeah.
Um very similar to an older, again, sort
of academic  research language
called OCaml, which is a variation off
of the pure functional language called
ML.
Um
long story short, one of the reasons why
functional languages are interesting is
because they encourage
um lack of side effects, or perhaps I
should say they discourage side effects.
You know, for example, when we call
system.console.writeline,
the functional guys say that method
doesn't do anything because it doesn't
return a value, but it has the side
effect of printing to the console.
Right? And they recognize that, you
know, certain side effects are necessary
and important in programming, like
printing to the console.
What the functional guys though
encourage is that you don't have side
effects. That if If modify an object,
quote unquote, you're not modifying the
object, you get a new copy of the object
with your modifications in it. Which if
you think about it is exactly how
system.string behaves.
Yep.
What this does for us in a lot of ways
is it helps reduce the surface area of
the code that we have to make thread
safe.
Mhm.
It's been sort of a long standing rule
in the Java space, thanks to Joshua
Bloch's Effective Java,
that, you know, if you can build
immutable objects, basically build the
equivalent of the string class, you
don't have to worry about putting
synchronization guards around it. Which
turns out to be very, very hard for most
programmers to get synchronization
exactly right.
And so, um I'll I'll actually plug uh a
buddy's book here, Brian Goetz, a friend
of mine from the Java space, has a book
coming out uh Java Concurrency Theory
and Practice,
Okay.
Concurrency in Practice. And because the
synchronization models of Java and C#
are so similar, I would recommend that
C# programmers, and VB programmers if
they really want to sort of up their
game,
um go take a look at this book when it
comes out. It'll be from Addison-Wesley.
It's supposed to come out probably by
end of second quarter, third quarter,
you know, somewhere in the late late
summer time frame. Um I think it's when
it would hit shelves. You know, and it
turns out, I mean, this is not a thin
book by any stretch of the imagination.
This is a hard problem to solve is
getting all this concurrency stuff
right.
And so, you know, functional languages
give us an opportunity to say, "You know
what? For a lot of what we want to do, I
really shouldn't have to worry about
synchronization if I take this basic
rule of thumb that says I want to prefer
immutable objects and immutable state."
Yeah.
And program in that mind frame as
opposed to a mind frame that says, "Oh,
well, I'm going to go and set a property
on that particular object and therefore
change state and therefore I have to be
thread safe, and so forth.
F sharp, um Scala,
um OCaml, they all sort of fall in that
same basic classification.
And, you know, there's a there's a sort
of a small, you know, cult community
growing up around F sharp, uh that's
coming out. Um you know, and and you
know, they're very interested in looking
at, for example,
can I use F sharp to make it much
easier, for example, to build uh user
interface?
You know, cuz a lot of the user
interface stuff that we deal with is in
in many respects, it's somewhat
functional in nature from the standpoint
that a lot of the things that we want to
do with in a user interface are, you
know, they are you could argue that they
are side effects, but underneath, a lot
of that stuff is basically functional in
nature. I do this, and this happens,
right? This is what's returned to me.
So, F sharp is interesting. Uh again,
it's another language coming out from
Microsoft research.
Mhm.
Um I don't know that we will ever see
ourselves writing WinForms code in F
sharp on a regular basis.
But again, I think what's happening here
is that there are people who are
experimenting with this stuff. There are
people who are looking at the you know,
the the the vast amount of knowledge
that's been going on in the academic
community,
and saying, "Hey, you know, there's some
goodness there. And let's pull that
goodness out, and let's apply it to what
we do as a as a practicing programmer,
and use it, you know?" One of the things
that comes out of the F sharp research
that Don Syme has been doing is a
toolkit called AbsIL, or Abstract IL.
Mhm.
It's basically a functional library for
manipulating assemblies on disk. So, if
you wanted to do some of what, you know,
some of the aspect guys have been doing,
I want to go through and and take an
existing assembly, and hack at it, and
inject
uh trace functionality. You know, kind
of like the enterprise instrumentation
framework does at runtime, but you don't
want to have to include all that code
yourself. You just want to say, "Look, I
want to have a little utility that will
weave in those tracing calls into the
production assembly because
I'm having a bug that I can't I can't
figure out where it's taking place."
This This thing will basically say, "All
right, let me go at that assembly. Let
me extract everything, feed it through a
sequence of functional calls where you
can hook into." This is very much
classic visitor pattern. You will hook
into it,
find the methods that you're interested
in, weave in the IL instructions that
you want, and emit it back out to disk.
Right? That's a very functional thing if
you think about it.
Yeah.
And the AbsIL toolkit makes it very,
very easy to do that if you understand
how functional programming works and how
F# works. So, F# becomes a natural
platform from which to do that.
Um, and that That's powerful. That's
some really, really powerful stuff.
So, again, I I I I really believe that,
you know, as a programming community,
you know, the next 5 years are going to
hold some you know, some incredible
innovation that are going to take place
in terms of languages because now we
finally have two platforms, three if you
include the Parrot work that's going on
in the Pearl community,
that, you know, we don't have to worry
about defining an entire runtime
environment about.
I just have to worry about how do I
translate
Yeah.
human-looking syntax into
machine-looking syntax.
Mhm.
That turns out to be much, much more
approachable problem for most people.
And this gets us into the realm of
domain-specific languages and, you know,
that that's easily another hour or so to
talk about.
Yeah.
Which we can do, uh, in another
interview, I guess. I think this was
very interesting. Anything else you want
to say because, uh, my list is, uh, I've
We've finished going through my
questions, basically. So, anything else
you want to say?
You know, just the um, you know, if
people are are interested part of what I
do as a consultant is I specialize in
looking at existing research topics
and you know, how they can apply to you
know, practically speaking to to
people's you know, technical problems.
Mhm.
So if there are you know, if any of what
we've talked about sounds interesting
but you're not sure how it apply to
you know, your company or if it would be
a useful fit drop me a note. We can talk
about you know, how I might be able to
help folks. You know, like I said I've
got a couple of books coming out in the
dot net and XML services space. So you
know, if you're interested in dot net,
if you're interested in how to use it
effectively, keep an eye on my blog.
I'll probably be announcing those when
they get closer to publication.
Mhm.
And just in general, you know, people
are interested in in programming
languages and and interested in some of
how this stuff could could make our
lives easier in the future.
There are tremendous number of resources
out there. You know, there is a dot net
languages page
similar to the Patrick Volkerding
languages for the Java VM page that
encourage people to sort of go up there
and and take a look at. You know, I I
will I will give props on my on my
weblog to the first person who hears
this interview and is able to tell me
what the Oak Sharp programming language
is.
Okay.
O Oak Sharp programming language.
Um you know, it's there's there's
there's suffice it to say that there are
certain languages out there that are
just silly.
Yeah.
But you know, the fact of the matter is
that you know, the the capacity, the the
capability, the the potentials
of language innovation on these two
platforms is just we're just seeing the
tip of the iceberg. There's so much more
we can do and to make our lives as
programmers that much more productive
and easier and so forth.
Yeah. And it's also a good thing for
developers I guess to look at languages
that use other paradigms than the OO
procedural stuff that Java or C# do
classically just to to expand their
horizon and learn what those what these
other Yeah.
Absolutely. Dave Thomas, uh who's one
half of the program of uh Pragmatic
Programmer,
uh same guy who's pushing Ruby.
Yeah.
Um he has a basic rule of thumb that I
encourage every programmer to follow,
which is to say learn a new language
every year.
Yep. Yep. And you know, not just you
know, if you're a C# programmer, you
know, don't go off and learn VB and call
that your language for the year because
VB is, you know, very fundamentally the
same thing as C#. Uh but go off and
learn F#. Go off and learn JScript,
right? The it it a buddy of mine in the
Java space, Glenn Vanderburg, does a
presentation called JavaScript, There's
a Real Programming Language in There.
And a lot of the dynamically typed
goodness that we like about Ruby and so
forth is present within JavaScript and
is there in the JScript.NET language,
which can be compiled.
And so there's, you know, there's a
tremendous amount of power even in the
languages that come out of the box in
Visual Studio that people don't know
about. But you know, go off and learn
F#. Go off and look at Scala. Go off and
look at, you know, Prolog. There are
some various Prolog.NET implementations.
Go off and look at Lisp and, you know,
its macro facility and how powerful
Yeah.
is. Um even to the point, you know, I
know a lot of the folks at Microsoft
will not be happy with me for saying
this, but I strongly suggest that
programmers go look at AspectJ and other
aspect-oriented programming languages
Yeah.
because there is a tremendous amount of
power there.
And, you know, decide for yourself
whether or not you like what AspectJ
does or dislike and why.
Yeah.
The act of going through and doing that
really sort of opens your mind up to
different ideas and different
possibilities. And then you walk onto a
project and you run across something
that's like, "Hey, I remember that I,
you know, that that that Prolog handles
this particular situation really, really
well. So, maybe I can do something.
Maybe I won't use A P sharp language to
do this, but maybe I will write
something that's similar to it, so that
you don't have to go off and reinvent
the wheel from scratch. You can work off
of established principles and
established guidelines, and you know,
save yourself
hundreds of hours of work.
Okay, Ted. Thank you very much. I think
that was a really cool discussion, and
Thank you. Thank you for having me.
Bye. Bye-bye.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio.
The Software Engineering Radio team
wants to thank Henning Pauly for
providing the music, as well as
lipsin.com for hosting and bandwidth.
For more information on the podcast,
past episodes, and feedback, go to
SE-Radio.net.